Plants have a family tree
植物的历史
stretching back nearly half a billion years.
可回溯至将近五亿年前
They have developed an extraordinary range of strategies to survive.
它们为了生存 发展出许多让人惊奇的策略
This tree is a bristlecone pine.
这是一棵刺果松
It's taken thousands of years to reach this size.
它花了几千年才长到这么大
It has seen empires rise and fall,
它看尽帝国崛起，衰微
kings, queens and presidents come and go
王朝兴盛更迭
and may have seen the sun rise more than 1.5 million times.
而且可能历经了 一百五十多万次的日出日落
Bristlecone pines are the oldest living things on Earth.
刺果松是世界上最长寿的生物
Bamboo is the fastest growing plant.
竹子则是生长速度最快的植物
It will be full-grown - 30 metres tall - in just 90 days.
短短九十天 就能长到三十公尺高
Like animals, plants are constantly competing for food.
植物和动物一样 无时无刻不在抢夺食物
Striving to produce offspring
努力繁衍后代
and battling against predators.
对抗掠食动物
They will deceive and, in some cases,
有的会欺瞒拐骗
they will even hunt.
有的甚至会猎食
We often don't notice such dramatic behaviour because,
我们对植物的惊人行为 往往视而不见
to our eyes, it happens so slowly.
因为对我们来说，它发生得太慢
But if time is compressed
但是若把时间压缩，换个角度
and you shift perspective to the plants' point of view, their world comes spectacularly to life.
由植物的观点出发 它们的世界顿时变得鲜活生动
The events in this woodland
把半年内在这片林地发生的事
can build to a view of half a year in less than a minute.
浓缩至不到一分钟
Like animals, plants need food and water.
和动物一样 植物也需要食物和水
But what sets them apart is their struggle for light.
植物需要阳光才能生长
Plants must have light in order to grow
所以它们为了得到充足的阳光
and will do anything to get as much as they need.
会各出奇招
The forest might appear to be the perfect place for plants to thrive.
森林似乎是 最适合植物生长的地方
Yet down here on the forest floor
但是对刚刚萌芽的新生植物来说
is one of the hardest places imaginable for a young plant to begin its life.
森林的地面是最难讨生活的地方
The canopy above is so thick that only a little sunlight can filter through.
上方的树冠层 浓密到只能透出一丝丝阳光
For this sapling, too little light means death.
这棵树苗得不到足够的阳光 只好黯然退出人生舞台
But plants on the forest floor need not be passive.
但是地面上的植物 也可以主动出击
If the light won't come to them, they can go to the light.
既然这里照不到光 就到有光的地方去
But they still have a problem.
但它们还是有一个问题
The light is 50 metres above them.
有光的地方离地面有五十公尺
So, they must climb.
它们只好往上爬
It's much easier to use another plant as scaffolding.
若能把其他植物当踏脚石 往上爬就轻松多了
But they won't get very high unless they can hold on tight.
但除非能紧紧攀住 否则爬不了多高
Like fingertips searching for a hold,
这棵长春藤的黏性吸盘
this ivy's adhesive pads grip the bark.
像寻找着力点的指尖一样 紧紧抓住树皮
Instead of sticking to the trees, some climbers use sharp claws.
有些植物不会紧黏在树干上 而是伸出利爪
The cat's claw creeper hooks its tendrils into the tiniest crevices
猫爪藤用卷须勾住微小裂缝
and hauls itself to the top.
把自己往上撑
With every metre it climbs, the light gets a little stronger,
每向上爬一公尺 阳光就变得更强一些
fuelling more growth.
进一步刺激它生长
This tendril of a passion flower seems to flail aimlessly in mid-air,
这株西番莲的卷须 看似漫无目的地在半空中乱挥
but in fact it's searching for an anchor point.
其实它在找一个着力点
Its tendril coils on itself, pulling the plant towards its support.
卷须盘绕起来 把植物拉向它的支撑物
In a matter of just days, these climbers make it to the canopy.
短短几天光景 这些攀缘植物就到了树冠层
Now with light in plentiful supply, these plants are able to flower.
它们来到明亮的阳光下 肆意地绽放花朵
Other plants have a different strategy
别的植物在拥挤的森林里 以截然不同的策略
to find the light they need in the crowded forest.
得到它们所需的光线
These are air-plants.
这些是气生植物
They grow on the upper branches of tall trees
它们生长在 高耸树木的上层树枝上
and spend their whole lives basking in the light.
终其一生都沐浴在阳光中
But growing 50 metres above the ground does have its drawbacks.
但是在离地五十公尺的地方生长 还是有缺点的
Most plants get water and nutrients through their roots in the ground.
大多数的植物利用根部 吸收土壤中的水分和养分
For an air-plant, with their roots planted in the tree tops,
在树梢扎根的气生植物
this isn't an option.
没办法这么做
But they have a solution.
但它们也有解决之道
First, the bare roots have an extraordinary ability
它们光裸的根部吸水力极强
to soak up water like blotting paper.
和吸墨纸不相上下
The slightest rain or mist, and they absorb every drop.
绝不放过一滴雨水或一丝雾气
They also have a way of gathering nutrients.
它们收集养分也自有一套方法
Their roots trap falling leaves
它们用根部收集落叶
which eventually rot and provide the plants with their own personal supply of compost.
落叶腐烂之后 成为它们专属的堆肥
20,000 different plants -
以这种惊人方式
orchids, bromeliads and ferns have taken up this remarkable lifestyle.
生存的气生植物有两万种 包括兰花，凤梨和羊齿植物
For a plant to thrive, it must not only get enough nutrients,
植物要茂盛生长 光是有养分还不够
but also the right balance of nutrients.
养分还得均衡才行
The soil in this waterlogged bog is very poor quality, lacking in nitrogen.
这片沼泽的土壤缺氮 所以土质很差
But these strange plants have an ingenious strategy.
但是这种奇特的植物 有一种别出心裁的策略
Their leaves are covered in tentacles,
它们的叶片上长满了触须
tipped with droplets of what appears to be morning dew.
触须顶端有一颗看似朝露的液滴
These droplets give the plant its name - the sundew.
所以小毛毡苔又叫做日露
They're sweet-smelling and attractive to many insects.
它们气味香甜，引来了许多昆虫
But they're also extremely sticky.
但它们也黏得不得了
Mosquitoes emerge in huge numbers from the boggy water
沼泽的蚊虫孵化时
and the sundews are ready.
小毛毡苔也准备好了
The sundew's tentacles are living fly-paper.
小毛毡苔的触须 有如活生生的捕蝇纸
Struggling only makes matters worse.
挣扎只会让情况越变越糟
With each contact, the plant tightens its grip.
每一次接触 都会让小毛毡苔卷得更紧
As more and more tentacles envelop the prey,
卷住猎物的触须越来越多
the droplets spread across its body.
液滴沾满了猎物的身体
Eventually, the insect is smothered and drowns in sticky fluid.
最后昆虫窒息，在黏液中淹死
Digestive enzymes break down the body into a nitrogen-rich meal
消化酵素把昆虫的身体 分解为一顿富含氮的大餐
which is absorbed by the plant.
由植物吸收
Without animal tissues this plant would not survive.
若少了动物的组织 这种植物也无法存活
But there's another carnivorous plant
但另一种食肉植物的
that's an even more sophisticated predator.
狩猎策略更高明
The Venus fly trap.
这是捕蝇草
Like the sundew, it makes itself very attractive,
它和小毛毡苔一样 都想办法让自己变得香甜可口
oozing nectar across the brim of each leaf.
每一片叶子的边缘都渗出蜜汁
But any visiting insect had better watch out for these six tiny hairs.
但是上门光顾的昆虫 得提防这六根小小的细毛
This fly has to tread carefully.
这只苍蝇得步步为营
If it strikes one hair,
如果它碰到一根细毛
it can carry on feeding.
可以继续进食
But a timer has been set.
但是计时器已经启动
A second strike in less than 20 seconds
如果在二十秒内碰到第二根细毛
and the fly is doomed.
苍蝇就没命了
An electrical impulse is triggered and the leaf snaps shut in just a fraction of a second.
一道电脉冲被触发 叶子迅雷不及掩耳地阖上
The tips lock together like prison bars.
叶缘的尖刺像监狱铁条般地交错
If the fly is very big, or very small, it may just manage to escape.
如果苍蝇体型很大或很小 也许还有一线生机
But most are trapped.
但绝大部分都逃生无门
And die.
最后一命呜呼
Ten days later, the trap re-opens.
十天以后，陷阱打开
All that remains is a husk.
苍蝇只剩下一个空壳子
The plant has finished its meal and resets itself
饱餐的捕蝇草重新设定
for its next victim.
等下一个倒霉鬼送上门来
But there is one time of year when the Venus fly trap
但每到特定时节
needs some of the visiting insects to live.
捕蝇草会给路过的昆虫一条生路
It needs their help to be pollinated.
它需要昆虫帮忙授粉
It sends up flowers on tall stems,
所以在远离下方陷阱的
well away from the danger of the traps below.
长梗上开花
Here, insects can feed safely on nectar.
昆虫可以放心地在这里吸食花蜜
In return, they provide a vital service,
并提供重要的
carrying pollen from flower to flower.
授粉服务
But the truce is only temporary.
但和平是短暂的
When pollination is over, it's back to business as usual.
授粉作用完成之后 一切恢复正常
80% of plant species on Earth have flowers.
世上的植物有百分之八十会开花
Flowers have just one role -
花朵只有一个功用
to enable the plant to produce offspring.
协助植物繁衍后代
Colour, perfume, nectar and shape
色彩，香气，蜜汁和形状
all act to make a flower irresistible.
为的是让花朵 拥有难以抗拒的魅力
Sunflowers grow to face the rising sun.
向日葵向阳生长
The warmth of the rays speeds the production of nectar
温暖的阳光加速花蜜产生
and this lures pollinators.
引来传粉的生物
One after another, hundreds of individual florets
数以百计的小花 接二连三地
produce pollen-covered stamens.
长出有花粉的雄蕊
And, like most flowers,
如同大部分的花朵
sunflowers establish a close relationship with animals
向日葵和动物发展出密切关系
in order to ensure their reproduction.
以确保物种的延续
As these bees busily feed on nectar,
忙碌吸食花蜜的蜜蜂
they unwittingly brush against the stamens, collecting pollen,
无意中收集了雄蕊上的花粉
and then carry it from flower to flower.
再带到下一朵花去
The sunflower is fertilised.
向日葵受精了
In the sun-drenched fields of southern France,
阳光普照的南法
the flowering season is a long one,
花期很长
but not all plants have this luxury.
但不是所有的植物都能这么奢侈
Cradle Mountain in Tasmania is blasted by bitter Antarctic winds.
来自南极的寒风 吹袭塔斯马尼亚的摇篮峰
To reproduce, the Richea honey bush must flower.
彩冠花要开花才能繁衍下一代
But the delicate parts of the flowers risk being damaged by the cold.
但花朵的纤弱部分极易冻伤
The plant appears to have an ingenious solution.
这种植物似乎有解决问题的妙方
The flower petals fuse together,
它的花瓣融合
forming an insulated, protective case around its stamens.
在雄蕊外形成 有保护绝缘作用的外壳
However, this creates another problem,
但这又产生了另一个问题
the flower case is so well sealed that, unfortunately,
密闭的外壳
it also keeps out pollinating insects.
也让授粉昆虫不得其门而入
During brief, sunny spells,
不过花朵在短暂的晴天会变暖
the flowers warm up and suddenly start producing nectar.
并突然开始制造花蜜
This attracts a bird - the Black Currawong.
这引来了一只黑噪钟鹊
It has the strength to rip open the flowers' outer casing
它为了吃花蜜
and gets its reward of nectar.
一把撕开花壳
At the same time, it exposes the delicate stamens to waiting insects.
同时苦候多时的昆虫 也终于等到雄蕊见天日的一刻
With luck, there's enough time for pollination
幸运的话 可以赶在寒风冻死花朵前
before the biting wind kills the flowers.
完成授粉
For some plants, the relationship with their pollinators is not collaborative,
某些植物 和授粉昆虫间的关系不是合作
it's war.
而是战争
Butterflies, and in such numbers,
这么多蝴蝶对任何花朵来说
would seem to be perfect pollinators for any flower.
应该都是最理想的授粉者
The Sandhill milkweed blooms every spring in the sandy meadows of Florida.
佛罗里达沙地草原的马利筋 在春天开花
It times its flowering perfectly to match the arrival
开花的时机正好碰上
of Monarch butterflies migrating here from Mexico.
大批从墨西哥 迁徙来此的帝王斑蝶
The Monarchs search out milkweed plants,
帝王斑蝶找上马利筋的原因
but they have something other than pollination on their minds.
并不是授粉
Rather than collect pollen, this female lays her eggs on the milkweed leaf.
这只雌蝶不收集花粉 而是在马利筋的叶片上产卵
This is the only plant the caterpillars can eat.
因为这是毛虫唯一能吃的植物
But the milkweed has a defence mechanism.
不过马利筋也有对策
As the caterpillar bites into a vein,
毛虫只要咬破叶脉
a kind of latex swells out engulfing it.
叶子就会流出一种胶乳包住毛虫
If the caterpillar isn't quick, it will drown...
如果毛虫动作太慢就会淹死
or find its jaws glued together.
或是被黏得张不开嘴
The plants' defence is so effective
马利筋的防御机制相当有效
that only one third of the Monarch caterpillars make it through the first day.
只有三分之一的毛虫 能撑过第一天
But the caterpillars that survive, grow in size and strength.
大难不死的毛虫 体型和力气与日俱增
And they go for the jugular.
然后开始攻击马利筋的要害
By carefully chewing through the main vein,
它们小心地咬破主脉
the caterpillar drains the leaf of latex
让叶片的胶乳流干
and cuts off its supply.
并阻断其供应
The milkweed's leaf is now defenceless
这下马利筋的叶片 再也无力反击
and the caterpillar eats in safety before preparing to pupate into a butterfly.
毛虫可以放心大嚼，然后成蛹化蝶
But after about ten days,
但是大约十天之后
it becomes clear why the plant has endured this onslaught.
马利筋忍受这种折磨的原因 变得很明显
A newly-hatched Monarch
刚羽化的斑蝶
simply can't resist the nectar-filled cups of the milkweed flowers.
完全无法抵抗 马利筋饱含蜜汁的花朵
As it moves across the flower heads,
蝴蝶在花头上移动时
its feet slide between grooves in the petals
脚擦过花瓣上
where the flower's pollen sacs are waiting.
藏有花粉囊的沟槽
As it flies off,
蝴蝶飞走时
the Monarch's feet hook out the pollen and carry it to the next flower
顺带把花粉带到下一朵花上
and pollination is achieved.
完成授粉
Although the milkweed has paid a heavy price,
虽然马利筋付出沉重代价
in the end it used the Monarch to get its way.
但最后 还是利用帝王斑蝶达到目的
Here in Dominica there's a plant that is so manipulative
但多米尼克 有一种工于心计的植物
that it has enslaved its pollinator.
它奴役了帮它传粉的动物
The bright red structures of the Heliconia
艳红赫蕉 鲜红色的构造
are actually modified leaves.
其实是叶子
These are its flowers.
这些才是它的花
They may be small, but they play a very important role
花虽然很小 但扮演了
keeping nectar well guarded at the very bottom of their long stems.
保护长梗底部花蜜的重要角色
The purple-throated Carib hummingbird, with its long curved beak,
鸟喙弯曲细长的紫喉加利蜂鸟
is the only bird capable of reaching this energy-rich food.
是唯一有办法 取得这种高能食物的鸟儿
But, cleverly, the Heliconia rations the amount of nectar it produces
但艳红赫蕉 狡猾地控制花蜜的生产量
to force the hummingbird into returning to the flower time and time again.
迫使蜂鸟再三回来吸食
Every time it makes a visit, it picks up more pollen on its beak and feathers.
蜂鸟每来一次 鸟喙和羽毛上就沾上更多花粉
The hummingbird is like an addict. Not only does it never stray,
蜂鸟像上瘾了一样 不但不会离开
but it will aggressively defend the flowers from thieves.
还会全力赶走 想来窃取花蜜的小偷
The plant is the master in this relationship.
在这段主奴关系里 植物才是主子
To ensure it gets pollinated, Heliconia has made the hummingbird its prisoner.
为了确保授粉成功 艳红赫蕉把蜂鸟变成自己的囚犯
A plant's problems don't end once it's been pollinated.
但植物授粉之后 还得面对别的问题
Plants need to spread their seeds as far away as possible,
植物必须尽可能地 把种子散播到远方
otherwise the adults will be in direct competition with their offspring.
不然子代会变成亲代的竞争对手
Here in South Africa,
南非
one flower achieves this by performing a remarkable trick.
有一种花朵 以惊人的方式达到这种目的
The plant waits dormant underground for more than a year.
灯台花在地底蛰伏了一年多
The first heavy rains for many months
连月干旱后的第一场大雨
are the trigger the plant has been waiting for.
是它等待多时的契机
Brunsvigia burst into flower.
灯台花开始怒放
Their timing is perfect.
而且时机刚刚好
These conditions are ideal for insects too.
因为现在的情况 对昆虫来说也很理想
The flowers enjoy a few days of frenzied pollination.
花朵享受了连续数天的狂热授粉
But it's not long before the searing heat returns.
但好景不常 天气再度变得酷热
The flowers start to wilt, shrivel and die.
花朵开始干枯，萎缩，死亡
Brunsvigia now needs to disperse its seeds widely,
灯台花必须把种子散播出去
yet the flowers still have their seeds trapped inside.
但种子还困在花里
But the flower isn't finished yet.
不过花朵的使命还没有结束
There are strong winds that blow across this landscape.
这里常会吹起一阵阵的强风
They snap the dry, dead stalks, sending each and every plant
干枯的花梗应声折断 灯台花骨碌碌地在地上滚动
cart-wheeling across the ground, casting seeds as it goes.
一边前进，一边释出种子
With the heat threatening to dry them out,
种子随时可能被炎阳晒干
the seeds' germination has to be immediate.
所以必须马上发芽
Deep in the forests of Borneo,
婆罗洲森林深处
some plants also use the wind to disperse their seeds,
有些植物也得靠风力播种
but in a completely different way - by giving their seeds wings.
但作法截然不同 它们的种子有翅膀
Some are helicopters that twist and turn their way down to the ground.
有的像直升机般 在空中旋转，飘落地面
But there is one that has a design
但有种植物的种子
that enables it to travel greater distances than all the others.
飞得比其他的都远
This is Alsomitra.
这是翅葫芦
Its football-sized pod is packed full of hundreds of extraordinary seeds.
它足球般大小的豆荚里 塞了好几百颗神奇的种子
Each is an almost aerodynamically perfect glider
每一颗种子都是可随着微风
that can be supported by even the slightest breeze.
翩然起舞的滑翔翼
Its paper-thin upswept wings
它们凭着纤薄上扬的翅膀
allow it to travel hundreds of metres through the forest.
飞到数百公尺外的地方
Once the seed hits the ground, the wings rot away
种子落地后 翅膀会腐烂
and the seed starts to germinate.
并开始发芽
A new Alsomitra vine starts to grow up towards the canopy
一株新生的翅葫芦在远离亲代的地方
and into the light - well away from its parent.
开始朝着洒满阳光的树冠层 奋力生长
There are other ways to disperse seeds
不过播种还有别的方式
and plants have evolved different tactics depending on where they live.
植物依生活环境不同 发展出不同的策略
In the desert of Arizona lives a master - the Saguaro cactus.
生长在亚利桑那沙漠里的 萨瓜罗掌是播种的大师
In the cool of the night, the cacti open their radiant flowers.
仙人掌花在凉爽的夜里绽放
They're soon visited by nectar-feeding bats
很快就吸引了以花蜜为食的蝙蝠
and as the bats move from cactus to cactus, they pollinate them.
蝙蝠在仙人掌间穿梭觅食时 完成了授粉
Each flower only lasts a night,
花只开一个晚上就谢了
but over three weeks, each cactus will produce more than 200 flowers.
但每一棵仙人掌在为期三周的花期间 可开两百多朵花
Every pollinated flower immediately begins to form a fruit at its base,
完成授粉的花 立即开始在底部
packed with thousands of seeds.
形成含有数千颗种子的果实
The mature Saguaro cacti are superbly adapted
成熟的萨瓜罗掌非常适合在
to survive out in the intense heat of the Sonoran Desert.
酷热的索诺拉沙漠中生存
But their seeds are delicate, and must find shade
但它们娇小的种子 必须要有遮荫
or they will scorch to death before they germinate.
不然还没发芽就被烤焦了
The seeds are covered with succulent sweet flesh -
种子外面的果肉多汁甜美
a meal that all sorts of desert creatures find irresistible.
是沙漠生物难以抗拒的美食
White winged doves are among the first to reach the ripening fruit.
白翅哀鸽率先赶来 享用成熟的果实
The seeds survive in the birds' stomachs
种子在鸟儿的肚子里存活
and will be carried many miles before being deposited in their droppings.
并在数公里外随粪便排出体外
Their own little packet of fertiliser.
这下连肥料都有了
But the cactus doesn't just rely on birds.
但仙人掌不只仰赖鸟类
Fallen fruit provides a bonanza for creatures on the ground.
落果对地面生物来说 有如天上掉下来的礼物
Foraging ants quickly gather seeds and flesh.
蚂蚁迅速搬走种子和果肉
That's if a tortoise doesn't get there first.
但有时会被沙漠陆龟捷足先登
The greater range of animals the cactus can get to eat its fruit,
来吃果实的动物种类越多
the more likely the seeds within will
仙人掌的种子就越有可能
be carried to the perfect place to germinate.
被带到适合发芽的地方去
The ants carry the seeds underground into their nests,
蚂蚁把种子带到地底的蚁窝
often excavated among the roots of trees.
蚁窝多半位于树根部位
The tortoise too will head for shade.
陆龟也要找个阴凉的地方
It spends much of its day cooling off under trees
它们白天多半在树下乘凉
where it's sure to leave undigested seeds in its dung.
顺便随着粪便排出 没有消化的种子
Now the seeds wait for the rains to come.
种子静静地等着下雨
Of the 40 million or so seeds a cactus produces in its lifetime,
仙人掌终其一生 可以制造四千多万颗种子
the chances are that only one will develop into a plant
但多半只有一颗会长成
that outlives its parent.
寿命超过亲代的子代
If it was lucky enough to find shade,
就算幸运地找到遮荫的种子
a seed will still take ten years to become a five centimetre tall cactus.
还是得花上十年才能长成 一棵五公分高的仙人掌
To reach the size of its parents, possibly ten metres,
要长成像亲代 那样的十公尺仙人掌
will take at least 100 years.
至少得花一百年
Plants can survive in the most unlikely and inhospitable places on Earth.
植物能在世上 最严酷恶劣的环境生存
Here on Socotra, a remote island in the Arabian Sea,
阿拉伯海偏远岛屿 索科特拉的旱季
the dry season is brutal.
让人吃不消
But this strange tree has a strategy to survive it.
但这种奇特的树木有生存妙招
The Dragon's Blood tree.
这是龙血树
The key to their success lies in their bizarre shape.
龙血树成功的关键 在于它们奇特的形状
They live on the mountain tops where there's little soil,
它们生长在土壤不多的山顶上
but there are critical compensations.
但山顶有很重要的好处
Occasional morning mists sweep across the high ground.
这里偶尔会飘过晨雾
The mist condenses on the skyward-pointing waxy leaves.
雾气在朝天的 蜡质树叶上凝结成水
The droplets run down to the centre of the trunk
水滴沿着树干
and down to its roots.
流到根部
Water is so precious that the tree cannot afford to waste any.
这里的水分太珍贵 一丁点都不能浪费
Drops that do escape and fall to the ground are not totally lost.
水滴到地上也不打紧
The tree's huge, densely packed crown acts as a parasol.
龙血树巨大浓密的树冠像把阳伞
It shades the ground so effectively
有效地遮住阳光
it allows time for the water to seep into the sand.
让水分有时间渗入沙地
And it also shades the network of roots that lie just under the surface.
同时也护住位于地表浅层的根部
Another plant shares this parched desert, but survives in a very different way.
这片干热沙漠还有另一种 生存策略很不一样的植物
The Desert Rose.
这是沙漠玫瑰
In really harsh conditions, it jettisons its leaves to minimise water loss.
在情况很恶劣的时候 它会放弃叶片以减少水分流失
Strangely, it chooses this time to flower.
它开花的时间很奇怪
Its bulbous trunk is like a barrel that stores water all year round.
沙漠玫瑰膨胀浑圆的树干 像个终年储水的水桶
It's so hardy it can grow out of bare rock.
生命力极强的沙漠玫瑰 可以生长在光秃秃的岩石上
It might seem that conditions can't get much tougher for a plant than here.
对植物来说 这里的环境应该算是最恶劣的
But, for some, the conditions are even harsher.
但有些植物生长环境的恶劣程度 有过之而无不及
Six hours ago, here on the coast of Australia,
六个小时前 这棵生长在澳洲海边的树
this tree was high and dry on a sandy beach.
还在一片干燥的沙滩上
For almost all plants, saltwater is lethal,
盐水几乎对所有植物 都有致命杀伤力
so submersion of this tree's roots by the tide twice a day should kill it.
这棵树的根部，一天被潮水淹没两次 它应该活不成了
Yet this Red Mangrove is flourishing.
但这棵红海榄却长得很茂盛
The retreating tide reveals the key to surviving the sea's assault.
潮水退去之后 它不畏海水蹂躏的关键昭然若揭
The mangrove's roots are covered in warty growths.
红海榄的根部长满了疣状突起
The growths surround pores that take in oxygen from the air
中间的气孔会在根部露出水面时
when the roots are above water.
吸收空气中的氧气
But the pores become useful in a quite different way
但气孔泡在水里的时候
when they're submerged again.
功用又不一样了
They allow water into the plant,
它们可以让水进入
but filter out 99% of the salt as it passes through.
但会滤掉海水中 百分之九十九的盐分
Any salt that gets in is pumped into a few sacrificial leaves
没被滤掉的盐分输送到 几片被选定牺牲的叶子
that turn yellow and are discarded.
这些叶子会变黄脱落
Plants can not only cope with being poisoned, parched and scorched,
植物可以抵挡毒素，干焦和炙烤
but they can also survive being frozen.
但它们也不怕被冰冻
In the world's northern forests,
北国森林的四季交替
the changing of the seasons creates its own challenges.
带来了一连串的考验
As summer moves to autumn,
夏末秋初时
plants prepare themselves for the toughest time of their year.
植物准备迎接 一年中最严酷的季节
Broad-leaved trees unveil what seems to us a colourful spectacle.
阔叶树上演了一出 让人膛目结舌的变装秀
But for these plants it is the beginning of a series of urgent
但对它们来说，这是一连串
and drastic survival strategies to cope with the coming cold.
紧急激烈求生策略的开始 以因应接下来的酷寒
They begin by pulling all the water and nutrients within their leaves
首先是把叶片中 所有的水分和养分
back into the trunk.
抽回树干
The last rays of useful sunlight are channelled
它们利用秋阳
into making a sugary anti-freeze that will protect the body of the tree.
制造含糖防冻剂 以保护树干
The green pigment - chlorophyll - disappears,
绿色的叶绿素消失
leaving purples, reds, oranges and yellows.
只剩下紫色，红色，橘色和黄色
Finally, the leaves die and the trees discard them.
最后枯死的树叶纷纷飘落地
As temperatures drop below freezing,
当温度降到冰点以下
the plants of broad-leaved forests settle down to hibernate until spring.
阔叶林中的植物进入冬眠 等待来年春天
Pine trees can survive much colder conditions.
松树可忍受更低的温度
They have anti-freeze in the leaves themselves,
它们的叶子里含有防冻剂
that means they can keep them all winter.
所以冬天不会掉落
The needle-like leaves also have a thick waxy coating
松针有一层厚厚的蜡质包复
that limits any water loss through pores.
减少水分流失
The winters here are long and hard.
这里的冬天漫长苦寒
The trees have to survive temperatures
树木必须忍受长达五个月
of down to -40C for five months.
摄氏零下四十度的低温
But one pine tree is capable of surviving even harsher conditions.
但有一种松树 可以在更恶劣的环境中生存
These pines live at the limit of life -
这些松树生长在美国西部
above 3,000 metres in the mountains of western America.
三千公尺以上的山区
Almost continuous freezing temperatures and savage winds make life so tough
这里是生命的极限 山上的低温和强风几乎终年不断
that these bristle cones only manage to grow for six weeks of the year.
所以刺果松每年的生长期 只有六个星期
Everything is about conserving energy.
它们的一切都以节能为导向
They hardly ever shed their needles, which can last more than 30 years.
刺果松的松针很少脱落 可以维持三十多年
After centuries of being blasted by storms,
忍受数百年的暴风雨吹袭后
a full-grown tree still survives with only a strip of bark a few inches wide.
一棵成年刺果松 只凭着数时宽的树皮生存
These trees live life at such a slow pace
这些树木的生活步调缓慢
that they can reach great age.
所以寿命惊人
Some are over 5,000 years old.
有的已经超过五千岁了
It's been said of the bristlecones,
有人说此地的刺果松
that to live here is to take a very long time to die.
连死亡过程都很漫长
As the northern spring approaches,
随着北国春天脚步的接近
the warming temperatures and increased day length release the land from winter.
与日俱增的温度和白昼长度 驱散了冬天的寒意
Plants that have lain dormant begin to grow again.
蛰伏了整个冬季的植物 再度开始生长
These have over-wintered,
这些植物
buried in the mud at the bottom of this frozen lake.
在冰冻湖底的 泥泞中度过冬天
The retreating ice allows the water to warm
消融的冰雪让水温回升
and this white water lily to flourish for another season.
这株香睡莲也准备 迎接另一个活跃的季节
And, as all the trees come out of their winter rest,
树木自冬眠中苏醒
the vivid green of new leaves returns to the land.
大地迸发新绿
From the frozen north to the southern deserts,
从冷冽北国到南方沙漠
the spring bloom symbolises the success of plants
春暖花开象征着植物
in surviving against the odds.
再一次克服逆境
But the most successful type of flowering plant
最成功的开花植物
is one that makes up 20% of all plant life on the planet.
是占全世界植物百分之二十的
Grass.
禾本科植物
There are 10,000 different species.
世上共有一万种 不同的禾本科植物
Today, they form the diet of many thousands of different animals.
禾本科植物 是数千种动物的食物来源
And a few grasses, particularly rich in nutrients,
而且有几种 营养特别丰富的禾本科植物
have developed a relationship with one animal
与某种动物建立了密切的关系
and together, the two have changed the world.
并共同改变了世界
10,000 years ago, we humans started to cultivate rice
人类在一万年前开始种植稻子
in order to harvest its food-rich seeds.
以收成其营养丰富的种子
Now, half of the world's population depends on it.
如今世上有半数人口以米为主食
But there is one other grass that has spread even further across the planet
但还有一种植物 因为与人类的关系
due to its relationship with humans...
在地球上的分布范围更广
wheat.
小麦
It underpinned the development of western civilisation.
小麦是西方文明发展的基础
Today, it covers more of the land than any other kind of plant.
现今小麦的复盖面积 比任何植物都多
Plants have been residents on land longer than animals
植物在地球上 出现的时间比动物早
and have had nearly half a billion years to evolve.
几乎花了五亿年的时间演化
During that time, they've diversified into countless forms
在那段期间植物发展出无数形态
and have colonised every habitat.
并进驻了所有的栖地
As well as collaborating with animals,
植物有时与动物合作
plants are sometimes their masters, exploiting them to their own advantage.
有时又是动物的主宰 为了私利剥削动物
Plants capture energy from the sun
植物撷取太阳的能量
and all life on land, directly or indirectly, depends on them.
所有生物不论是直接还是间接 都必须仰赖植物而活
So, ultimately, plants fuel the diversity of life on Earth.
所以植物是 推动生物多样性的力量
To see the behaviour of plants as they struggle to survive
拍摄植物努力生长的过程
presented a unique challenge.
是一个很特殊的挑战
The plants team had to employ many techniques,
植物拍摄小组必须利用许多摄影技巧
including time-lapse and high-speed photography.
包括缩时摄影和高速摄影
They filmed in jungles, deserts, swamps and plains,
他们不只到过 丛林，沙漠，沼泽，平原
but they also spent many hours shooting in a converted barn
也在艾斯特外改造的仓库里
just outside Exeter.
花了许多时间进行拍摄
All under the watchful eye of green-fingered cameraman Tim Shepherd.
拍摄工作都在绿手指摄影师 提姆雪柏的严密掌控下进行
Filming plants in time-lapse takes so long
以缩时摄影拍摄植物非常耗时
and is so susceptible to changes in light levels and weather conditions
且易受光线的变化 和天候状况的影响
that some key sequences had to be filmed in this studio.
因此有些场景必须在棚内拍摄
In time-lapse, a camera takes a series of pictures
缩时摄影是在一段时间内
over an extended period of time,
拍摄连续的画面
so, when played back, the action appears speeded up.
因此放映时像是加速的动作
These sunflowers actually take three days to open,
这些向日葵其实 花了三天的时间开花
but are seen opening in a matter of seconds.
现在看起来像是只用了几秒钟
The most complex time-lapse the team attempted
摄影小组所拍出 最复杂的缩时摄影效果
showed an entire growing season in an English woodland in one continuous shot.
就是用一个连续的镜头表现英国森林里 整个生长季开花的情形
A shot that took two years to create.
这个镜头花了两年才完成
I think this is going to be the spot.
我想就是这里了
As the producer Neil Lucas
制作人尼尔卢卡斯带提姆
leads Tim and Mick Connaire the graphic designer out to the location,
和美术设计师米克康乃尔
he explains his idea.
到选定的地点，同时解释他的想法
- Well, this is one that I thought...
我的想法是这样子
- That's a lovely rock. - Just here.
- 好漂亮的石头 - 就是这里
And I think that'd be great to have the brambles growing along.
要是有刺藤沿着生长应该很不错
It will be a tracking shot through the wood with plants growing,
这是一个森林里的推轨镜头
flowers blooming and the woodland coming to life
随着植物生长，花苞开放
over the course of a year.
森林在一年的时间里 展现生命的活力
We're condensing that one year down into less than a minute.
我们把一年 浓缩成不到一分钟的时间
We're going to have to have them all coming out at the same time,
并且让所有植物同时生长开花
multiple passes.
这要分很多次拍摄对吧
How long does a foxglove take to grow?
毛地黄要多久时间生长
Well, if we start just before the buds are about to open
如果我们从有花苞前开始算
and you've got the whole long spike,
一整支长串的花穗
then top to bottom that's probably about three weeks.
从上到下大概要三个星期
So, even if you wanted to, you couldn't shoot the plants here
所以就算你想 也没办法在这里拍摄
because, three weeks, the weather's going to change,
那表示三个星期
you've got the day-night
天气会变化 还有白天，晚上
and also just leaving the equipment here running,
机器也要放在这里
it's not feasible, is it?
不太可行，对吧
You just have to imagine the changes
你只要想象 在这里拍三个星期可能的变数
that would happen here in three weeks
可能发生的状况太多了
and if that was all joined together and one frame the plant might be there
这个镜头植物还在这里
and you take a shot of it an hour later and,
一小时后拍下个镜头
if the wind's blowing, it's over here somewhere
它被风吹到那里
and then you join those two shots together...
然后把两个画面放在一起
It just won't work.
根本就不能用
So what we've got to do is not only have we got to produce a move
所以我们必须建造一个场景
that is exactly the same repeatable move,
是可以完全复制重建的
a track that can be built exactly the same again in a studio.
推轨镜头的轨道 也可以完全在棚内复制重搭
Build exact models of every object in here so we can put plants
这里每一样物件都要制作模型
in the right places and then time everything,
我们将植物放在同样的位置
- so they grow just as
然后植物刚好
the camera happens to be pointing at them.
在镜头拍摄下慢慢生长
- Yes. - OK.
没错
The scale of the challenge is dawning on them.
他们开始了解这个挑战的难度
Months of planning lie ahead.
拍摄前还有好几个月的准备工作
The following spring, the team head back to the wood.
第二年春天摄影小组回到森林
With no road access,
因为没有道路可以进入
manpower is the only way to get the tonnes of equipment into position.
要搬运几吨重的摄影器材就位 人力是唯一的办法
Everyone's wondering how this will turn out, including the locals.
大家都很好奇拍摄的效果会是如何 包括当地的居民
Go up about an inch.
往上大概一英
Straight now. Start like that.
现在打直 就是那样
Position now is 221556.
位置是二二一五五六
We've done it wrong.
我们弄错了
That's pulled it. Hang on - that's pulled it terribly.
卡住了，等等 卡得很严重
- Did that snap? - No,
- 断掉了吗 - 没有
it's pulled this wheel round.
只是卡到这个轮子
Two days of building, levelling, test runs
耗时两天的搭建，校准，测试
and even a few minor disasters
甚至还发生几个小问题
and finally the track is ready to run.
终于轨道搭好可以使用了
OK, that's pretty close.
好，很接近了
If you move your...
你看得到那块青苔吗
Can you see that little bit of lichen? Go to 8,900.
到八九00的位置
Accuracy is paramount.
准确度是最重要的关键
Yeah, whatever we shoot in the studio,
不论我们在棚内拍摄什么
it's got to match this landscape exactly,
都一定要和外景实际位置相符
so unless we know precisely where everything is relative to the camera,
所以除非我们准确地知道 每样东西相对摄影机的位置
there's no way of placing the plants in the studio in the right place.
不然是不可能 在棚内摆得一模一样的
So we have to measure the hell out of it.
所以我们一直测量个没完
Oh, bloody hell, it's spot on. Look at that.
可恶，就是那里，你看
- So 250. - OK.
所以位置二五0，好
Shot by shot and step by step,
一步一步 一个镜头接着一个镜头
the camera inches its way back up the 30 metre track.
摄影机慢慢拉上 三十公尺长的轨道
Well, that's working.
搞定了
This is only the background shot.
这还只是背景的拍摄
There is still a huge amount of other filming to be done.
还有更多的拍摄工作尚待完成
The track has to be rebuilt exactly as it is on location back in the studio
摄影机的轨道要在棚内重搭 而且要搭得和外景一模一样
- a task that would take weeks to get right.
可能要花上好几个星期
Right under the tree at the end of the rock.
在树底下，石头边
Using the detailed measurements taken in the wood,
利用森林里精准的测量
the position size and shape of every structure has to be matched precisely.
各个物体的位置，尺寸，形状 都必须和在森林里完全相同
- 35.
一点三零，三五
- 35, yeah.
三五，对
The slightest discrepancy will put the team back to square one.
任何一点误差 都可能使摄影小组必须重新来过
Chicken-wire and polystyrene form the rocks and trees of the woodland.
铁丝网和保丽龙 做成森林里的石头和树木
Blue screen is used to cover every inch of the set
再由蓝色布幕复盖每一时场景
to allow the original shot to be mapped on later in graphics.
之后才能让 原来拍摄的画面显示在上面
Once built, and with the plants placed in their exact locations,
背景搭好 植物摆放在确切的位置
filming can start.
接下来可以开始拍摄了
The stars of the show finally make an appearance.
主秀的明星终于要登场了
Timing is everything.
各种植物开花
With each plant taking up to three weeks to flower
最多要三个星期 时间点是最重要的
there's only one chance of getting it right.
拍摄工作只有一次的机会
A year later and thankfully so far all had gone to plan.
一年后，幸好一切都按照计划走
The final stage is to bring all the pieces together seamlessly -
最后阶段要将所有画面 完美地剪接在一起
a challenging task for any graphic designer.
这对任何一位 美术设计师都是挑战
We've got things overlapping
我们把不见得同时成长
that wouldn't necessarily grow at the same time,
开花的植物放在一起
but all the growth of each individual plant is absolutely accurate.
但是每种植物的生长 都是实际拍摄的
It's exactly what they would do. We're just seeing it in a shorter space of time.
它们的生长情形确实如此，我们只是在 很短的时间内看到这个过程
That big rock in the foreground at the end of the shot
镜头最后那个前景的大石头
that we wanted to try and get stuff climbing on,
我们希望植物在它上面慢慢生长
that's worked really, really well.
结果效果非常好
This is the bramble here.
刺藤爬在这里 我们必须非常仔细测量
Had to measure it so carefully so we knew exactly where these things were,
才能准确地知道所有东西的位置
how round they were, how deep they were from the camera.
物体的比例是否正确 距离摄影机有多远
Then when we take the blue out of that
然后我们把蓝色部分拿掉
you can see that the plants start to sit into the shot
你看植物就出现在画面上了
exactly where we wanted them to be,
准确的在我们要的位置
things appearing from behind the tree,
在树的后面
forming on the top of the rock. - That's fantastic.
一或在石头上 一太棒了
If I switch those off
你看，如果我把它们按掉
you can see how just how neatly they slot into the shot.
就可以看到它们插入画面的位置
If we play it, you can see
现在我们播放影片，你可以看到
that everything's sticking in pretty well.
所有的植物很自然地融入画面里
96 layers, 15 tracks and two years later,
九十六个影像层，十五条音轨 费时两年
the shot is finally complete.
这个镜头终于完成了
A 60-second shot that proved to be one of the most complex
这个六十秒的镜头 果然是自然历史影片中
ever attempted in natural history film-making.
所拍摄最复杂的镜头